Finding Aid for Frank E. Robbins Papers 1907-1961
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frank E. Robbins Papers 1907-1961 1934-1960
Robbins, Frank Egleston, 1884-
University of Michigan professor of Greek; Assistant to the President; papers include correspondence, writings, pencil sketches and photographs, topical files.
852177 Aa 2 AA
1.6 linear feet
1 volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Frank E. Robbins and came to the Bentley Historical Library in various accessions from 1937 to 1962. Donor no. 1273.
The collection is open for research.
Frank Egleston Robbins was born September 9, 1884 in Westfield, Massachusetts. He attended Wesleyan University in Connecticut, and received the degree of Bachelor of Arts in 1906 and Master of Arts in 1907. In 1911, he graduated from the University of Chicago with the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.
Robbins came to the University of Michigan in 1912 as a teacher in Greek. Robbins became the unofficial keeper of university affairs and history. He was an authority of academic protocol, and was responsible for academic celebrations involving costume and procedure. His involvement included serving as chairman of the general committee for President Hatcher's inauguration, and consulting on the proper academic procedure for hosting foreign dignitaries and honorary degree recipients.
In 1921, he was appointed to the position of Assistant to the President and continued until his retirement in 1953. He was the assistant to four university presidents during his career. Serving also as director of the University Press starting in 1930, Dr. Robbins oversaw the publication of hundreds of scholarly books and informative pamphlets on the university. As director of the University Press, Robbins assisted in the publication of the Middle English Dictionary and a dictionary of Elizabethan Proverb Lore. Robbins had his own research published as well, including writings on Ptolemy, Tetrabiblos, and other contributions on astrology and mathematics in miscellaneous papyri. Dr. Robbins served as the editor of the Michigan Quarterly Review, as well as emeritus assistant to the president and director emeritus of the University Press. He died in 1963 in Ann Arbor after a brief illness.
The papers of Frank Egleston Robbins consist of materials from his work as the assistant to the university president, and his other activities within the university. The series are: Correspondence, Miscellaneous, Writings, Visual Materials and Assistant to the President Topical Files.
Subjects:
Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Egleston family.; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888.; Poetry.; Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Classical Studies.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan. Press.; University of Michigan. Secretary.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Apostles Club (University of Michigan); Graduation ceremonies.; Robbins, Frank Egleston, 1884-; University of Michigan--Commencements.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Contributors:
Cather, Willa, 1873-1947.; Frost, Robert, 1874-1963.; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series deals mainly with Dr. Robbins' work as the assistant to the university president. In addition to official internal writings, he communicated with prospective students needing more information on the University of Michigan, alumni, and other academic institutions.
  - 1911-1960, 20 folders (Box 1)
    (includes 2 Willa Cather letters written in 1924, 4 Robert Frost letters in 1924, and 1 letter from Sinclair Lewis in 1927)
  - Concerning the naming of a naval vessel for the city of Ann Arbor 1940-1945 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series consists of items such as Dr. Robbins' notes on University of Michigan football games, a university chapel notice from 1893, and some biographical and genealogical material about the Egleston family. This series also includes a scrapbook of newspaper articles from the early 1920s about the University of Michigan. The scrapbook is divided into the following sections: Alumni, Building program, G. D. Eaton, Hospital-Homeopathy, Housing, Installation, Lectures-Addresses-Speeches, Legislature, Students, and Miscellaneous.
  - Genealogy of the Egleston family in Michigan (Box 1)
  - Student records/personnel information (Box 1)
  - U-M Football games diagrams 1932-1960 (Box 1)
  - University Chapel notice 1893 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1920-1924 (Box 1)
    (filed with bound volumes)
- Writings
  The Writings series includes plays, an opera, poetry and ballads, and drafts of published articles.
  - Ballads, Poems, and parodies (Box 1)
  - Plays and Opera 1920-1939 (Box 1)
  - Paper entitled "Asa Gray's Visit to Ann Arbor" (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 1)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series are comprised of original sketches and drawings, and photographs. Most of the sketches are of University of Michigan buildings and faculty and staff. Some of the sketches were drawn during university meetings.
  - Sketches
    - Christmas greetings designed, and featuring illustrations, by FER (Box 1)
    - Maps designed by FER and featuring Michigan, the University of Michigan campus, and locales used by prominent mystery writers and other authors in their writings (Box 1)
    - Pencil sketches of University of Michigan faculty and administrators, "doodled" during University Council meetings (Box 1)
    - Sketchbook of University of Michigan buildings undated (Box 1)
    - Sketchbook of campus and other views, c.1937 (Box 1)
    - Sketchbook of University of Michigan faculty and administrators (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1884-1963
    - Portraits; photographs of commencement ceremonies; and group portrait of the Apostles Club (Box 1)
- Assistant to the President Topical Files circa 1936-1955
  The Assistant to the President Topical Files contain a mixture of papers in the period of 1936 to 1955 relating to the specific responsibilities of the assistant to the president and papers pertaining to Robbins' particular scholarly interests and hobbies.
  - Academic costume code (Box 2)
  - Academic dress (Box 2)
  - Association memberships (Box 2)
  - Association memberships survey 1942 (Box 2)
  - Cap and gown miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Certificate samples (Box 2)
  - Columbus letter translation (Box 2)
  - Committees
    - Academic calendar (Box 2)
    - Alumni relations (Box 2)
    - Commencement procedure (Box 2)
    - Fees and scholarships (Box 2)
    - Library exchange (Box 2)
    - Official publications (Box 2)
    - Student-Faculty Relations Committee (Box 2)
  - Data on degrees (Box 2)
  - Diploma, change in (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of faculty services (Box 2)
  - Faculty (deceased) (Box 2)
  - Freshman finance (Box 2)
  - Maturity and old age (Box 2)
  - "Murder at Manistee" article (Box 2)
  - Oriental art (Box 2)
  - Patents (Box 2)
  - Phoenix Project (Box 2)
  - President's Report
    - General (Box 2)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 2)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 2)
  - Ptolemy translation (Box 2)
  - Research and achievement at Michigan (Box 2)
  - Scheduling events (Box 2)
  - Scholarships
    - Phebe A. I. Howell Scholarship (Box 2)
    - Emma Clarissa Malcolm Scholarship (Box 2)
  - Stone, Ralph
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Bronze tablet; Detroit's 250th birthday festival (Box 2)
    - History of U of M Club of Detroit (Box 2)
  - Trollope, Anthony (Box 2)
  - University buildings, data on (Box 2)